[Music]
foreign
can be a painful recurring inflammatory
process of the lining of our mouths and
similar to other chronic inflammatory
conditions DNA damage due to oxidative
stress-free radicals is thought to play
a role normally free radical production
is balanced with antioxidants however if
the free radical concentration gets too
high and our antioxidant enzymes and the
antioxidants we get in our diet cannot
adequately compensate for these radicals
the balance is shifted in a pro-oxidant
direction which can lead to oxidative
damage within our body okay so do those
with recurring canker sores have fewer
antioxidants more oxidation and more DNA
damage yes yes and yes more pro-oxidants
and more oxidative stress in their
bloodstream lower antioxidant status and
more DNA damage suggesting it might be
possible for antioxidants to help but
you don't know
until you put it to the test 16 boys and
girls around age 12 with recurring
canker sores given a whopping 2 grams of
vitamin C a day that's considered the
tolerable upper daily limit for adults
before you start getting diarrhea and
1200 milligrams may do that in a 12 year
old but it's all about risks and
benefits how did they do 15 out of 16
cut the number of canker sores they were
getting at least in half and three
months before they started the vitamin C
they averaged four canker sores but in
three months they were on it had less
than one on average then they tried
stopping the sea for another three
months and the ulcers started coming
back and so they added the seed back and
the canker sore rate dropped again what
about applying antioxidants directly
like a turmeric gel a gel containing two
percent curcumin the yellow pigment of
the spice Turmeric swabbed directly onto
the canker sores twice a day it did seem
to significantly reduce pain intensity
and ulcer size compared to Placebo
compared to a gel containing no active
ingredient
but it would be nice to see a comparison
to some active treatment and from an
independent research group not funded by
the curcumin gel manufacturer and
here it is a randomized clinical trial a
generic two percent curcumin gel versus
a prescription steroid gel and the
curcumin worked just as well providing
strong evidence that can be used as an
effective and safer alternative to
steroids for the treatment of recurring
canker sores
but if you remember topical honey beat
out the same steroid for both ulcer
healing compared to the steroid and pain
reduction compared to the steroid so if
you're going to use something topically
honey seems best but what if you just
want to swallow something instead but
something that doesn't give you diarrhea
31 patients with recurring canker sores
were split up into two groups getting
either 20 milligrams of yeast beta
glucan fiber a day or Placebo that's the
amount found in just an eighth of a
teaspoon of brewer's yeast or
nutritional yeast in the placebo group
no significant change whereas in the
yeast group ulcer severity was cut
nearly in half so that's something else
you can try
if it's an antioxidant thing can you
just eat a plant-based diet lots of
fruits and vegetables and treat it that
way
that's never been put to the test though
what plant-based diet could also make
things worse if one is not ensuring a
regular reliable source of vitamin B12
through supplements or fortified Foods
for example 30 year old woman with four
years of recurring canker sores eating
so few animal products and no
supplementation she became vitamin B12
deficient and started feeling weak and
tired numbness and tingling so they
immediately started her on B12 and
thankfully her B12 deficiency symptoms
got better but so did her canker sores a
rapid in complete recovery within weeks
of starting B12 after years of suffering
we've known B12 deficiency could lead to
canker sore since the 70s so much so
that a recommendation has been made to
consider B12 deficiency any time you see
a patient with recurring canker sores in
fact a number of nutrient deficiencies
may do it if you compare the lab tests
of those with recurrent canker sores to
those without more than half of the
canker sore group showed evidence of
hematinic deficiencies in other words
blood forming nutrient deficiencies
compared to less than one in 10 of the
non-canker sore group so we're talking
like iron deficiency and folate
deficiency in addition to B12 deficiency
so they gave them supplements and their
canker sores improved especially among
those who didn't have a family history
of canker sore problems
okay so you could see how Vitamin and
mineral supplements might help people
who are deficient but might a supplement
like vitamin B12 help even people not
B12 deficient apparently so as the title
says cyanocobalamin the most common form
of supplemental B12 may be beneficial in
the treatment of recurrent canker sores
even when vitamin B12 levels are normal
they took a group of 72 patients with
frequent canker sores and gave them B12
regardless of what their levels were
and in 96 of cases they got better and
that was among both those who started
out to fish in and those who started out
with regular B12 levels in their blood
but there was no control group so you
don't know how many would have gotten
better anyway and they injected the B12
and injections can have an even greater
placebo effect than pills especially
perhaps with something like B12 which is
a striking mad scientist looking ruby
red color in the syringe
but there never been a randomized
double-blind placebo-controlled trial of
oral B12 for canker sores until there
was
thousand micrograms of sublingual B12 a
day for six months and it took five
months but eventually the duration of
canker outbreaks the number of ulcers
and the level of pain were significantly
reduced and again regardless of the
initial vitamin B12 levels in their
blood so B12 deficient or not vitamin
B12 supplements seem to help
by the end of the study twice as many in
the B12 group appear to have been cured
so vitamin B12 supplements represent a
simple inexpensive low risk effective
treatment though it appeared to take
months before it starts working whereas
if you apply B12 directly to the canker
sore a randomized double lymphocal
control trial of a B12 ointment applied
directly to the canker sores you can get
at least significant reduction in pain
within two days compared to Placebo and
again it doesn't matter whether your
vitamin B12 deficient or not
[Music]
thank you